Guide to the William Barrett Pease Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Barrett Pease papers
1877-1887
MS 15
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box)
Correspondence and financial records of William Barrett Pease, son of a New Haven bookseller and Civil War veteran. Most of the letters are from members of his wife's family and relate to Pease's real estate holdings in Brooklyn. A letter (1879 Jul 3) from Samuel Chapman Armstrong, the founder of the Hampton Institute, offers Pease a position at the Institute.
Pease, William Barrett, 1844-1903
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edward Ingraham, 1955.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence. II. Financial Records.
Scope and Contents
The William Barrett Pease (1844-1903) Papers consist of one box of primarily business and family letters and financial statements covering the period 1877-1887. Originally mounted in chronological order in one volume, the papers are now alphabetically arranged in two series of 41 folders. Most of the letters are from F.W., John, and Henry Cook, his wife's uncle and cousins, and concern Pease's real estate holdings in Brooklyn.
These papers were donated to the Yale University Library by Edward Ingraham in 1955.
Biographical / Historical
William B. Pease was the son of Thomas Huntington Pease (1815-1890), a New Haven bookseller. After enlisting as a private in the 15th infantry regiment of the Connecticut Volunteers, he was commissioned as a Lieutenant in the 8th regiment of U.S. Colored Troops in 1862. The regiment served in Florida for a time and was then transferred to Virginia where it was one of the first units of the Union Army to enter Petersburg. After the war he went with the regiment to Brownsville, Texas to assist in restoring order. In 1867 he received a commission as First Lieutenant in the 11th regiment of the regular army. The only letter in the collection connected with his service with the Colored Troops is one in folder one from Samuel Chapman Armstrong dated 1879 July 3. Armstrong, the founder of Hampton Institute, offers Pease a position at the Institute, but these is no further information on the subject in the papers. Of the later events in Pease's life, little has been recorded. For a time he served as Captain at Fort Omaha, Nebraska and from at least 1899 until his death he 1903 he lived in Samobor, Austria. Pease married Mary Frances Cook and was the father of four girls. The letters from non-family members are mainly concerned with his investments in real estate and railroads, financial notes and mortgages, and army supplies.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Businessmen; Armstrong, S. C. (Samuel Chapman), 1839-1893; Pease, William Barrett, 1844-1903; Hampton Institute
- Correspondence, 1877-1887; Series I; 3" Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence includes letters arranged in alphabetical order according to last name of sender or recipient, and arranged in chronological order within each folder. Much of the correspondence is with Pease's cousins, Henry F., and John C. Cook; his father, Thomas Huntington Pease (1815-1890) of New Haven; and an uncle, R.W. Cook. Also included are some business letters.
  - Armstrong, Samuel Chapman (1839-1893), 1879 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brown, M.B., 1877 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bunce & Benedict, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Carpenter, W.H., 1879 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clarke, E., 1882, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cook, F.W., 1878, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cook, Henry F., 1878-1879 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cook, John C., 1878-1887 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cook, William E., 1880 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ely, H., 1882 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Foot, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Foster, Fred W., 1880 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Foster, James H., 1877, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jennings, S.A., 1880 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Lee, J.M., 1880 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lemington, M.J., 1879 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lindenberger, I., 1881-1882 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Macnaughten, Ramsay, 1880-1881 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Mackall, J.O., 1881 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Max Meyer & Brother, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mills, E.A., 1880-1882 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Adrian Muller & Son, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Nanton, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Newman, Clement D., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Norris, W.F., 1887 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Paul, Augustus C., 1879-1880 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Pease, Thomas H., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Redfiell, H.J., 1880 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Rockefeller, C.M., 1879, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Shiverick, Charles, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Taylor, William, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Thayer, G.D., 1880 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Towar, George W., 1880 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Wallace, William, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - White, George W., 1878-1884 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Wild, J.E., 1879 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Wittenan, Anna., 1884 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Pease, Miriam Halsey "Mimi" (Pease's Daughter), undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Financial records, 1878-1886; Series II; 3" Box 1
  Financial Records contain statements of accounts, bills, and an assessment of the value of houses owned by William B. Pease.
  - Statements of accounts, 1878-1879 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Financial statements of Mrs. William B. Pease, 1878-1886 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Assessment of value of houses owned by William B. Pease, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)